<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Blue Card guide</string>
    <string name="action_settings">Settings</string>
    <string name="bc_system" formatted="false">
        <![CDATA[
        <p>The blue card system:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>&nbsp;is a key prevention and monitoring system of people working with children and young people in Queensland</li>
            <li>&nbsp;aims to minimise the risks of harm to children and young people by contributing to the creation of safe and supportive environments, and</li>
            <li>&nbsp;is founded on the principle that all children have a fundamental right to be protected from harm.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Key benefits:</p>
        <ul>
			<li>&nbsp;the <strong>past</strong> is risk managed though the initial assessment, which determines a person&rsquo;s eligibility to work with children, based on known police or disciplinary information</li>
            <li>&nbsp;the <strong>present</strong> is risk managed through police information of all blue card or exemption card holders, which is continuously monitored so any changes are actioned appropriately, and </li>
            <li>&nbsp;the <strong>future</strong> is risk managed by service providers, who are required to implement child and youth risk management strategies and review them annually.</li>
        </ul>
        <h2>Purpose </h2>
        <p>The purpose of the blue card system is to contribute to the creation of safe and supportive environments for children and young people when receiving services and participating in activities which are essential to their development and wellbeing, such as child care, education, sport, and cultural activities.</p>

        <p> While many people are familiar with the blue card itself, it is important to be aware that the initial blue card screening is only the first component of a three part system which considers past, present, and future risks:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>&nbsp;Blue card screening to determine a person`s eligibility to work with children and young people based on their known past behaviour</li>
            <li>&nbsp;Ongoing monitoring of all blue card holders and applicants which enables action to be taken to protect children and young people if the person is charged with a concerning offence, and</li>
            <li>&nbsp;Mitigating future risk through the requirement for organisations providing child related services to develop and implement child and youth risk management strategies.</li>
        </ul>
        <h2>Blue card screening</h2>

        <p>This  assesses a person&rsquo;s eligibility to hold a blue card or exemption card based on  their known past police and disciplinary information. This process also  disqualifies certain people upfront and prevents people from working with  children whose past behaviour indicates they are not eligible to enter  regulated child-related employment.</p>
        <h2>Ongoing  monitoring</h2>
        <p>The police information of all card holders and applicants is monitored.  If the information changes, immediate steps can be taken to protect children from harm. Service providers and  card holders are also monitored to ensure they are meeting their blue card system obligations and  providing safe environments for children.</p>

        <h2>Child and youth risk management strategies</h2>

        <p>Organisations who provide  child-related services must have policies and procedures in place to identify  and minimise the risk of harm to children. These risk management strategies are  monitored and must be reviewed annually.</p>

        <h2>What is the Working with Children Check?</h2>

        <p>The Working with Children Check (also known as the blue card check) is a   check that assesses:</p>
        <ul>
            <li>&nbsp;any national charge or conviction (including spent convictions and pending and non-conviction charges) for an offence (even if no conviction was recorded) </li>
            <li>&nbsp;child protection prohibition orders (whether a person is a respondent or   subject to an application) </li>
            <li>&nbsp;disqualification orders </li>
            <li>&nbsp;if a person is subject to reporting obligations under the <em>Child   Protection (Offender Reporting) Act 2004</em> or <em>Dangerous Prisoners (Sexual   Offenders) Act 2003</em> </li>
            <li>&nbsp;disciplinary information held by certain professional organisations   including teachers, child care licensees and foster carers, and </li>
            <li>&nbsp;information that the Police Commissioner may provide in relation to police   investigations into allegations of serious child-related sexual offences, even   if no charges were laid. </li>
        </ul>

        <p>A person whose application is approved is issued with a positive notice   letter and a blue card. </p>

        <p>If a person&rsquo;s application is refused, they are issued with a negative notice   which prohibits them from carrying on a business or providing regulated child-related   activities.  </p>

        <p>Find out the <a href="https://www.bluecard.qld.gov.au/Differencebetweenbluecardcheckandpolicecheck.html">difference between a Working with Children Check and a Police Check</a>.</p>

        <h2><a name="exemption" id="exemption"></a>What is an exemption card?</h2>

        <p>If you are a registered teacher or police officer in Queensland, you do not apply for a blue card and should instead apply for an exemption card when   providing regulated services to children which are outside of your professional   duties.</p>

        <p>More information about exemption cards can be found on the <a href="https://www.bluecard.qld.gov.au/pdf/infosheets/Information-Sheet-Exemption-cards-for-Police-Officers.pdf">Police Officers Information Sheet</a> (PDF, 310KB) and <a href="https://www.bluecard.qld.gov.au/pdf/infosheets/Information-Sheet-Exemption-cards-for-teachers.pdf">Registered Teachers Information Sheet</a> (PDF, 399KB).</p>

        <h2><a name="rms" id="rms"></a>What is a risk management strategy?</h2>

        <p> Safe environments don&rsquo;t just happen, they require ongoing planning, commitment   and maintenance. Organisations falling within the scope of the blue card system   are required to implement child and youth risk management strategies which   address eight minimum requirements. The purpose of these strategies is to ensure   that organisations have appropriate policies and procedures in place which assist in identifying   and minimising the risk of harm to children and young people in regulated service   environments.</p>
        <p>Read more about <a href="https://www.bluecard.qld.gov.au/risk-management.html">Child and youth risk management strategies</a>.</p>
        <p>&nbsp;</p><p id="publish-date"><strong>Last Updated:</strong>  <!-- #BeginDate format:Sw1 -->27 September, 2016<!-- #EndDate -->
        </p>
    ]]></string>
    <string name="who_can_get" formatted="false"><![CDATA[
            <h2>Who can apply for a blue card?</h2>
        <p>Employers, volunteer coordinators and education providers are responsible for applying for blue cards on behalf of their employees, volunteers or trainee students. Business operators or people seeking to operate a business working with children are responsible for applying directly to Blue Card Services for a blue card. However, if you have had your blue card suspended, are a negative notice holder or a disqualified person, you are unable to apply for a blue card and should contact Blue Card Services for further information.</p>
		</br>

		<h2>What is the blue card check?</h2>
		<p>The blue card check assesses:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>&nbsp;national criminal history, of all charges and convictions (including spent and not recorded)</li>
			<li>&nbsp;child protection prohibition orders (whether a person is a respondent or subject to an application)</li>
			<li>&nbsp;disqualification orders</li>
			<li>&nbsp;if a person is subject to reporting obligations under the Child Protection (Offender Reporting) Act 2004 or Dangerous Prisoners (Sexual Offenders) Act 2003</li>
			<li>&nbsp;disciplinary information held by certain professional organisations including teachers, child care providers and foster carers </li>
			<li>information that the Police Commissioner may provide in relation to police investigations into allegations of serious	child-related sexual offences, even if no charges were laid.</li>
		</ul>
		<p>A person whose application is approved is issued with a positive notice letter and a blue card. If a person’s application is refused, they are issued with a negative notice which prohibits them from carrying on a business or providing child-related activities in the categories regulated by the Working with Children (Risk Management and Screening) Act 2000. </p>

		<h2>Are there any exemptions?</h2>
		<p>Exemptions from blue card screening apply in relation to certain categories of regulated childrelated employment and business. An	exemption from screening requirements in relation to one category does not mean that a person will be exempt in relation to another category. For details about any relevant exemptions visit our website. </p>

		<h2>How long does a blue card application take to process?</h2>
		<p>Blue card applications where no police or disciplinary information is received are generally processed within 28 working days provided the form is complete and no further information is	required from the applicant. </p>

		<h2>When can I commence work?</h2>
		<p>Paid employees can commence working while their blue card applications are being processed, but volunteers and people carrying on a business must wait for their blue card to be issued before commencing regulated childrelated work.</p>
		<p>It is important to note that if volunteer and business applicants submit their renewal applications at least 30 days prior to the expiry of their card, they can continue to work while their renewal application is being processed. </p>
		<p>Blue Card Services sends out renewal notices	approximately 10 weeks prior to the expiry of a blue card holder’s card to remind them to submit their application. Organisations employing applicants under these conditions should address potential risks in their risk management strategy</p>
]]></string>
    <string name="what_i_need" formatted="false"><![CDATA[
    <h2>What necessary for apply for a blue card?</h2>
    <p>A blue card is a special case of a residence permit. Conditions may vary in different EU countries. There are also some general necessary requirements:</p>
    <ul>
    <li>&nbsp;citizenship of a non-EU country</li>
    <li>&nbsp;employment contract for 1 year or more with the official employer of the selected country</li>
    <li>&nbsp;documentary proof of qualification from the list of highly demanded specialties. For example, a diploma</li>
    <li>&nbsp;health insurance contract or statement</li>
    <li>&nbsp;the applicant`s safety for the country and society. A document on the absence of problems with the law.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>General provisions are given, the EU consists of 28 countries, therefore the Directive gives the right to each of them to make withdrawals or enter quotas for certain professions and thus to protect their labor market. </p>
]]></string>
    <string name="list_of_spec" formatted="false">
        <![CDATA[
                <h2>In demand professionals.</h2>
        <p>In each country there are more demanded professions, there are less. In general, the following specialists are most often in demand:</p>
		</br>

		<ul>
			<li>&nbsp;medical workers</li>
			<li>&nbsp;experts in various fields of jurisprudence</li>
			<li>&nbsp;teachers of the exact sciences</li>
			<li>&nbsp;trading managers</li>
			<li>&nbsp;engineers </li>
			<li>&nbsp;financial analysts </li>
			<li>&nbsp;IT-specialists. </li>
		</ul>

]]>
    </string>
</resources>
